# Erika P Ordonez

Arlington, TX, (682) 300-9188

www.linkedin.com/in/ErikaOrdonezB, epordonez@hotmail.com

## **Optimization RF Engineer**

Highly motivated Telecommunications Professional with extensive experience and real world experience managing telecommunication projects and data analysis for major companies including AT&T and Cisco. Possesses a proven ability to meet the challenges and quickly assimilate to the newest technologies, skills, and concepts. Recognized as a creative problem solver able to effectively work alone or as part of a team.

- Project Management
- Communication (written and oral)
- Fluent in Spanish (reading, written and oral)
- KPI Analysis
- Cluster Optimization
- Layer 3 Analysis

- KPI Performance Improvement
- Troubleshooting 2G, 3G, LTE, VolTE
- Top offenders/VIP routes

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Telecommunications Software**: MapInfo, Nokia NetAct Suite, Cisco SON Self-Optimization Network Tool, Tems Discovery, Google Earth, Atoll, Windcatcher, M2000, UNET, Genex Assistant, FMA, Netnumen, Optimi X-parameters, PCI scanner and Spectrum Analyzer

Languages: Python, R, Oracle SQL Microsoft Office: Excel (Vlookup, VBA, Macros), Word, PowerPoint

#### **EDUCATION**

Master of Science, Quantitative Finance, University of Texas at Arlington, TX, GPA:3.9

5/2019

Bachelor of Science, Electronics and Telecommunications Engineering, Polytechnic School ESPOL Ecuador

1/2009

### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

# Perfosolut, Guayaquil, Ecuador IT Technical Support

9/2016 - 12/2017

- Fixed systems and work with internal customers to determine needed hardware or software changes.
- Designed, implemented, and managed wired and wireless LAN networks with firewall and router configurations and anti-malware solutions.
- Configuration VoIP phones for the office, analysis of SIP protocol.
- Updating tests for the Moramon Android application for monitoring radio bases of Movistar Ecuador using ADB and Android Studio. https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=ec.sekai.moramon&hl=en\_US

# **Huawei Technologies,** Mexico DF, Mexico

12/2015 – 7/2016

## Radiofrequency Consultant AT&T 3G/LTE Project

- Designed and delivered optimized reporting for 15 AT&T clusters in Mexico, Puebla, and San Luis Potosi during Pre-Launch and Post-Launch phase.
- Optimized VoLTE by creating drive testing scenarios to verify SIP, RTP protocols and QCI5 and QCI1 Bearers functionalities and coverage Metric KPIs
- Socialized and implemented new optimization reports with the customer.
- Monitored and reviewed statistical data covering dropped calls, blocked calls, access failures and handovers for 850, 1900, and 2100 frequencies within a 3G and LTE networks.

- Brought performance indicators to 98% by enhancing accessibility and retainability through the addition of 2000 missing neighbors.
- Improved kpi from 85% to 98% through enhancing accessibility driven by reporting.

## Cisco Systems, Guayaquil, Ecuador

9/2014 - 10/2015

## **Self-Optimization Network Consultant**

- Directed the configuration of 1,100 3G sites in the self-optimization network system platform.
- Conducted training for 10 Engineering Claro staff members, educating each on all SON functions and features.
- Led customer meetings to establish completed milestones.

## OSC Telecoms & Security Solutions, Guayaquil, Ecuador Radiofrequency Consultant Telefonica 3G Project

1/2014 - 8/2014

- Executed the design strategies for the optimization of the 2G and 3G network with the Telefonica staff.
- Monitored kpis for 50 sites on daily/weekly basis, and implemented process improvement for access failures and drop calls performance indicators.
- Collaborated directly with the Operations team to better troubleshoot outstanding network issues.

## Huawei Technologies, Quito, Ecuador

2/2012 - 1/2014

#### Senior Radiofrequency Engineer 3G / LTE CNT Project

- Assisted in streamlining project progress by directly interacting with customers and cross functional teams.
- Performed root cause analysis of top customer complaints and troubleshoot issues when possible.
- Conducted training and provided oversight to new engineers, highlighting optimization procedures and the best practice use of telecommunication tools.

#### Telefonica, Quito, Ecuador

5/2010 - 1/2012

#### Senior Network Quality Engineer

- Quickly identified sites with bad quality within May 2010 to Jan 2012 by effectively monitoring the performance of 3G Nokia cellular network main clusters.
- Coordinated with maintenance staff to troubleshoot actions and prepare reports for follow-up meetings.
- Efficiently resolved and closed 60 customer complaint tickets for low voice quality and data service in the Nokia network.
- Support for the Moramon Android application for monitoring radio bases of Movistar Ecuador using ADB and Android Studio.

# Huawei Technologies, Ecuador, Perú, Colombia, Barbados

5/2008 - 5/2010

## LATAM Radiofrequency Engineer

- Completed 10 cluster final reports for initial tuning of the Colombia 3G network.
- Reached the coverage indicator by 95% by optimizing coverage between 850 and 1900 networks for the Peru project.
- Elaborated the coverage simulation map of the 3G network for the Barbados project and participated in meetings with customers and staff.

#### **TRAININGS**

## **VolTE Training, Remote** by Gessner Rivas

5/2019

VolTE Network Architecture, Volte Optimization and Volte Performance KPI

Huawei LTE Training, Quito, Ecuador

11/2013

## **ZTE 3G Training, Quito, Ecuador**

05/2011

3G Basic Theory, 3G Cell Parameter Planning, 3G RF Optimization, 3G KPI

#### **ASSOCIATIONS AND SCHOLARSHIPS**

Wayne Watts Graduate Fellowship Scholarship recipient

Beta Gamma Sigma, Member

FMA National Honor Society, Member

ALPFA,Member

Arlington Nooners Toastmasters Club, Member

**REFERENCES** 

Gessner Rivas, Principal RF Engineer

grivas\_1@hotmail.com

linkedin.com/in/gessner-rivas-0401251a